PG 048, Bradley Field World War II Activities
Connecticut State Library
Bradley Field World War II activities
1942-1945
Connecticut State Library
United States. Army Air Forces
.5 cubic feet (217 photographs)
Views of military life and training at the air base, the Sixth War Loan drive, redeployment, officers and medal presentations to families of servicemen.
PG048
T001771
Historical Note
On January 23, 1941, Governor Robert A. Hurley sent a proposal to the Connecticut General Assembly requesting the state buy land to lease to the United States Army for an air base. The U.S. Army had earlier indicated to state officials that it wished to have a base for fighter planes in or near Connecticut as part of the nation's defensive grid though the attack on Pearl Harbor had not yet occurred. In response, the state acquired 1,700 acres most of which was then a tobacco plantation. The tract was purchased and then leased to the federal government for $1.00 a year for twenty-five years. The field, which at the time was named the Windsor Locks Army Air Base, became ready for airmen and troops early in the summer of 1941.
The air base was later officially renamed "Army Air Base, Bradley Field, Connecticut," on January 20, 1942, but more familiarly called Bradley Field in honor of Army Air Corps Second Lieutenant Eugene M. Bradley. Lt. Bradley's P-40 fighter plane crashed after he went into a routine dive during training and failed to come out on August 21, 1941. Bradley hailed from Pushmataha County (according to multiple sources either Antlers or Dela) in Oklahoma, and arrived at the air base three days before his fatal accident. He was the first of many pilots to die in training accidents at the field.
Scope and Contents
This collection of 217 black and white photographs is a representative survey of the aspects of military life and training on the base from 1942 to 1945. All the photos are numbered, identified, and stamped "Official U.S. Army Air Corps photo" on back. Activities represented include, among others, the Sixth War Loan drive, an open house for the public, redeployment, multiple training exercises, the training of Chinese fighter pilots, day-to-day life, and medal presentations to servicemen or the families of those missing in action.
Arrangement
The photographs are numbered from 1 to 217.
Related Material
None.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Bradley Field (Windsor Locks, Conn.); Military bases -- Connecticut; Soldiers, Black; Women soldiers; World War, 1939-1945
Persons:
Baldwin, Raymond E. (Raymond Earl), 1893-1986; Bradley, Eugene M., 1917-1941; Finter, Clyde W; Johnson, Hubert E; Lovell, George E; Massey, Ivor
Organizations:
United States. Army Air Forces; United States. Army. Air Corps. Air Base Squadron, 29th; United States. Army. Air Corps. Base Headquarters, 29th; United States. Army. Air Corps. Base Unit, 121st; United States. Army. Air Corps. Fighter Control Squadron, 94th; United States. Army. Air Corps. Air Base Group, 30th; United States. Army. Air Corps. Materiel Squadron, 41st
Places:
Enfield (Conn.); Hartford (Conn.); Simsbury (Conn.); Weatogue (Conn.); Windsor Locks (Conn.)
Document Types:
Photographs
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Alternative Form Available
Links to digital images of the documents are provided in the "List of Photographs" section.
Acquisition Information
This collection was presented to the Connecticut State Library by the public relations officer from Bradley Field at the end of the war.
List of Photographs
- Photographs, 1942-1945
  - Lieutenant Eugene M. Bradley, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 1)
  - 30th Air Base commander and officers, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 2)
  - 30th Air Base Group en masse, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 3)
  - Senior non-commissioned officers, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 4)
  - Headquarters & Headquarters Squadron, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 5)
  - 41st Material Squadron, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 6)
  - Colonel Clyde V. Finter, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 7)
  - Colonel George E. Lovell, Jr., circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 8)
  - Major Charles W. Dewey, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 9)
  - Lt. Colonel Gwen G. Arkinson, 1943 March 15 (Envelope 10)
  - Lt. Anita Cox, 1943 April 26 (Envelope 11)
  - Colonel Ivor Massey, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 12)
  - General Hunter and Colonel Massey, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 13)
  - Captain John W. Farrell, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 14)
  - First Sergeant Edythe Griffiths, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 15)
  - Colonel Hubert E. Johnson, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 16)
  - Sergeant Beatrice McCuistion and George Ortseifer, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 17)
  - First Lieutenant R.E. Larson, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 18)
  - Staff Sergeant Raymond Dunn with Commissary Employees, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 19)
  - First Lieutenant R.E. Larson, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 20)
  - First Lieutenant R.E. Larson, Staff Sergeant Raymond Dunn, and Miss Irene Kristofac, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 21)
  - First Lieutenant R.E. Larson and Miss Irene Kristofac, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 22)
  - Staff Sergeant Dolphus W. Banks and an unknown cook, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 23)
  - Staff Sergeant Dolphus W. Banks and First Lieutenant Morris F. Schwartz, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 24)
  - Singing at Bradley Field Station Hospital, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 25)
  - Book cart at Bradley Field Station Hospital, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 26)
  - Bishop McAuliffe and Father Donoghue, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 27)
  - Bishop McAuliffe and Father Byrnes, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 28)
  - Auxiliary Marjorie H. Buckland and Private Mearl Luvass, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 29)
  - Lieutenant Colonel and Mrs. Henry G. Woodward, 1942 January 30 (Envelope 30)
  - Cadets leaving Bradley Field for flying training, 1942 March 25 (Envelope 31)
  - Governor Robert A. Hurley is welcomed to Bradley Field, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 32)
  - Victory parade in Enfield, Connecticut, 1942 May 16 (Envelope 33)
  - Bishop McAuliffe and Colonel Clyde V. Finter, 1942 May 29 (Envelope 34)
  - Mass officiated by Father Joseph F. Donoghue, Base Chaplain, 1942 June 17 (Envelope 35)
  - Chemical decontamination of a vehicle, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 36)
  - Mess personnel operate a field kitchen, 1942 (Envelope 37)
  - The band plays in front of the barracks, 1942 July 14 (Envelope 38)
  - Colonel George E. Lovell, Jr., 1942 December 5 (Envelope 49)
  - Patient receives a box of homemade delicacies, 1942 July 9 (Envelope 40)
  - Major General James E. Chaney at Bradley Field, 1943 January 13 (Envelope 41)
  - M.P. Squadron on parade, 1943 April 3 (Envelope 42)
  - M.P. Squadron on parade, 1943 April 3 (Envelope 43)
  - M.P. Squadron on parade, 1943 April 3 (Envelope 44)
  - M.P. Squadron on parade, 1943 April 3 (Envelope 45)
  - Bivouac, 1943 June 12 (Envelope 46)
  - Bivouac, 1943 June 12 (Envelope 47)
  - Bivouac, 1943 June 12 (Envelope 48)
  - Bivouac, 1943 June 12 (Envelope 49)
  - Frederick E. Maples conducts Sunday worship, 1943 June 12 (Envelope 50)
  - Bivouac, 1943 June 12 (Envelope 51)
  - Bivouac, 1943 June 12 (Envelope 52)
  - Open ranks inspection, 1943 June 16 (Envelope 53)
  - Open ranks inspection, 1943 June 16 (Envelope 54)
  - Open ranks inspection, 1943 June 16 (Envelope 55)
  - Women's Army Corps weather class, 1943 June 19 (Envelope 56)
  - Unloading equipment, 1943 June 23 (Envelope 57)
  - On the Weatogue range, 1943 June 24 (Envelope 58)
  - On the Weatogue range, 1943 June 24 (Envelope 59)
  - On the Weatogue range, 1943 June 24 (Envelope 60)
  - On the Weatogue range, 1943 June 24 (Envelope 61)
  - On the Weatogue range, 1943 June 24 (Envelope 62)
  - Cleaning firearms, 1943 June 26 (Envelope 63)
  - Firing a furnace, 1943 June 26 (Envelope 64)
  - Mechanic repairing a tank, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 65)
  - Photo technician, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 66)
  - On parade at Bradley Field, 1943 July 12 (Envelope 67)
  - Messing in the field, 1943 July 17 (Envelope 68)
  - Gas decontamination drill, 1943 August 7 (Envelope 69)
  - Gas decontamination drill, 1943 August 7 (Envelope 70)
  - Gas decontamination drill, 1943 August 7 (Envelope 71)
  - Gas decontamination drill, 1943 August 7 (Envelope 72)
  - Gas decontamination drill, 1943 August 15 (Envelope 73)
  - Blockbuster, 1943 September 9 (Envelope 74)
  - Blockbuster, 1943 September 9 (Envelope 75)
  - Service at an outdoor chapel, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 76)
  - Mr. and Mrs Anthony B. Kowalski are presented the Air Medal for their son, 1943 October 31 (Envelope 77)
  - Boxing match, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 78)
  - Basketball game at the Base Gymnasium, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 79)
  - General Henry H. Arnold, Commanding General, 1944 June 3 (Envelope 80)
  - Retreat parade, 1944 June 3 (Envelope 81)
  - American Red Cross helps out, 1944 June 27 (Envelope 82)
  - Master Sergeant H.V. Whitbeck, 1944 July (Envelope 83)
  - Master Sergeant H.V. Whitbeck, 1944 July (Envelope 84)
  - Mock court session, 1944 July 5 (Envelope 85)
  - Outing, 1944 July (Envelope 86)
  - Jewish Welfare Board outing, 1944 July 12 (Envelope 87)
  - Smoke screen demonstration, 1944 July 19 (Envelope 88)
  - P-47 Turbosupercharger graphic, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 89)
  - Familiarization of the machine gun, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 90)
  - Mrs. Ruth H. McGregor, Mr. Courtice H. Berry, and Captain J.W. DiGeronimo, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 91)
  - Ordinance section at Bradley Field, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 92)
  - Open House, 1944 August 1 (Envelope 93)
  - Open House, 1944 August 1 (Envelope 94)
  - Open House, 1944 August 1 (Envelope 95)
  - Open House, 1944 August 1 (Envelope 96)
  - Open House, 1944 August 1 (Envelope 97)
  - Open House, 1944 August 1 (Envelope 98)
  - Junior Birdmen at Open House, 1944 August 1 (Envelope 99)
  - Retreat ceremony, 1944 August 1 (Envelope 100)
  - WAC Day, 1944 August 8 (Envelope 101)
  - Civil Air Patrol cadets, circa 1942-1944 (Envelope 102)
  - Staff Sergeant George Watson, 1944 August (Envelope 103)
  - Staff Sergeant George Watson, 1944 August (Envelope 104)
  - First Air Force Chemical Warfare Team, 1944 September 2 (Envelope 105)
  - Chemical warfare demonstration, 1944 September 2 (Envelope 106)
  - Chemical warfare demonstration, 1944 September 2 (Envelope 107)
  - Demonstration of a P-47 at Bradley Field, 1944 September 6 (Envelope 108)
  - P-47, 1944 September 15 (Envelope 109)
  - Softball game, 1944 September 22 (Envelope 110)
  - Softball game, 1944 September 22 (Envelope 111)
  - African-American troops at Bradley Field, 1944 September 23 (Envelope 112)
  - Sergeant Blanche Rubenstein and Staff Sergeant John J. Barrett, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 113)
  - Camouflage class, 1944 October (Envelope 114)
  - Fire drill at A.A.F., 1944 October 9 (Envelope 115)
  - Boxing match, 1944 October 20 (Envelope 116)
  - Boxing match, 1944 October 20 (Envelope 117)
  - Mechanical difficulties, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 118)
  - Unloading winter coal supply, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 119)
  - Inspection of train tracks, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 120)
  - Herman Trombley and Private First Class John Danhardt, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 121)
  - Transfer of freight cars, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 122)
  - Charles Minck of Danbury receives the Air Medal for his son, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 123)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Charles E. D'Arcy receive the Air Medal for their son, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 124)
  - The Combat Infantryman Badge is presented to Michael A. Hetes, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 125)
  - Mrs. Dorothy Labaff is presented the Air Medal for her husband, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 126)
  - Mrs. James Ivain is presented the Air Medal for her son, 1944 October 21 (Envelope 127)
  - Parade at Bradley Field, 1944 September 23 (Envelope 128)
  - Parade at Bradley Field, 1944 September 23 (Envelope 129)
  - African-American troops at Bradley Field, 1944 September 23 (Envelope 130)
  - Corporal Thelma I. Terwilliger, 1944 November (Envelope 131)
  - Corporal Mary Alice Kadelak O'Brien, 1944 November (Envelope 132)
  - Private Aura M. Carpenter, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 133)
  - Sergeant Jean Clouthier, 1944 September 23 (Envelope 134)
  - Private John Dawalo, 1944 November 25 (Envelope 135)
  - Private J.R. Klugh, 1944 November 25 (Envelope 136)
  - Sergeant R.C. Hobbs, 1944 November 25 (Envelope 137)
  - Sergeant Jack Taylor and Sergeant John Connors, 1944 November 25 (Envelope 138)
  - Medal presentation, 1944 November 29 (Envelope 139)
  - Sergeant Mary Pantelis and Major Albert S. Aiken, 1944 November 29 (Envelope 140)
  - Private Virginia S. Peirson, 1944 November 27 (Envelope 141)
  - Corporal Loretta P. Kenward, 1944 November 27 (Envelope 142)
  - Prayer at the Base Chapel, 1944 December 2 (Envelope 143)
  - Base Library, 1944 December 2 (Envelope 144)
  - N.C.O. Club, 1944 December 2 (Envelope 145)
  - N.C.O. Club, 1944 December 2 (Envelope 146)
  - National Polish Home Dance Hall, 1944 (Envelope 147)
  - Service Canteen, 1944 (Envelope 148)
  - Y.M.C.A. swimming pool, 1944 (Envelope 149)
  - Masonic Service Center, 1944 (Envelope 150)
  - Y.W.C.A. snack bar, 1944 (Envelope 151)
  - Rolling Kitchen at Hartford Railroad Station, 1944 (Envelope 152)
  - Hartford U.S.O., 1944 (Envelope 153)
  - Sixth War Loan, circa 1944 November 20 - December 16 (Envelope 154)
  - Blind officer, circa 1944 November 20 - December 16 (Envelope 155)
  - Sixth War Loan, circa 1944 November 20 - December 16 (Envelope 156)
  - Sixth War Loan, circa 1944 November 20 - December 16 (Envelope 157)
  - Sixth War Loan, circa 1944 November 20 - December 16 (Envelope 158)
  - Sixth War Loan, circa 1944 November 20 - December 16 (Envelope 159)
  - Sixth War Loan, circa 1944 November 20 - December 16 (Envelope 160)
  - Blockbuster and airplane display, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 161)
  - Blockbuster and airplane display, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 162)
  - Post Exchange, 1944 (Envelope 163)
  - Lieutenant Betty Gunn assists a surgeon, 1945 January 25 (Envelope 164)
  - Lieutenant Elizabeth Van Ormer and Lieutenant Betty Gunn, 1945 January 25 (Envelope 165)
  - Lieutenant Mary G. Reidy helps Private Bernard Massey, circa 1945 January 25 (Envelope 166)
  - Lieutenant Mary G. Reidy and Captain John R. Lucas, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 167)
  - Lieutenant Colonel Frank R. Fleming and Captain Verena Zeller, 1945 January 26 (Envelope 168)
  - Movement, 94th Fighter Control Squadron, 1945 April 3 (Envelope 169)
  - Movement, 94th Fighter Control Squadron, 1945 April 3 (Envelope 170)
  - Movement, 94th Fighter Control Squadron, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 171)
  - In the control tower, 1945 May 22 (Envelope 172)
  - Redployment of belongings, 1945 May 22 (Envelope 173)
  - Paper work during redeployment, 1945 May 22 (Envelope 174)
  - Physical examination during redeployment, 1945 May 22 (Envelope 175)
  - Working on an aircraft, 1945 May 22 (Envelope 176)
  - Working on an aircraft, 1945 May 22 (Envelope 177)
  - Unloading a truck alongside a train, 1945 May 22 (Envelope 178)
  - Piles of gear on the ground and in a truck, 1945 July 7 (Envelope 179)
  - Men load onto a truck during redeployment, 1945 July 7 (Envelope 180)
  - B-17 aircraft lined up, 1945 August 7 (Envelope 181)
  - Women mechanics, 1945 July 7 (Envelope 182)
  - Mechanical work, 1945 August 7 (Envelope 183)
  - Refueling aircraft, 1945 August 7 (Envelope 184)
  - Aircraft lined up, 1945 August 7 (Envelope 185)
  - Aircraft on the move, 1945 August 7 (Envelope 186)
  - Aircraft and four servicemen, 1945 August 7 (Envelope 187)
  - Boarding a train, circa 1945 May 22 - August 31 (Envelope 188)
  - Emergency War Service vehicle alongside train, circa 1945 May 22 - August 31 (Envelope 189)
  - Redeployment train, circa 1945 May 22 - August 31 (Envelope 190)
  - Redeployment train, circa 1945 May 22 - August 31 (Envelope 191)
  - Gear transfer, circa 1945 May 22 - August 31 (Envelope 192)
  - Gear transfer, circa 1945 May 22 - August 31 (Envelope 193)
  - Jewish service, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 194)
  - Jewish service, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 195)
  - Jewish service, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 196)
  - Base Library, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 197)
  - A crowd at the Post Exchange, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 198)
  - Post Exchange, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 199)
  - Recreation Hall, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 200)
  - Recreation Hall, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 201)
  - Recreation Hall, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 202)
  - Recreation Hall, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 203)
  - Base Library, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 204)
  - Control Tower in operation, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 205)
  - Chinese trainees learn the fundamentals of flying fighter planes, 1942 (Envelope 206)
  - Chinese trainees are tested for color blindness, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 207)
  - Physical examination, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 208)
  - Chinese trainees eating, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 209)
  - Chinese trainees at a dance, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 210)
  - Master Sergeant John P. Carey, Ordnance, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 211)
  - Master Sergeant John P. Carey, Ordnance, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 212)
  - Major General Hunter and Colonel Johnson, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 213)
  - Corporal R.J. Thomas and Governor Raymond E. Baldwin, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 214)
  - Mrs. Celia Tedone and Mrs. Frank T. Tedone receive the Distinguished Flying Cross and Air Medal, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 215)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Charles Aldrich receive the Air Medal for their son, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 216)
  - Mrs. Marge Hadfield is presented the Air Medal for her husband, circa 1942-1945 (Envelope 217)